In this 3-video series,
I show the science behind the
pros and cons of the flu vaccine,
pneumonia vaccine,
and shingles vaccine.
"Benefits and Side Effects of the Flu Vaccine"
Every year,
influenza typically kills
between 4,000
and 20,000 Americans,
though the death toll
for the 2017 to 2018 season
was estimated at 80,000,
making it one of the deadliest
in the last half century.
Most hospitalizations
and 90 percent
of flu-related mortality
occur in those
65 and older,
and most over the age of 75.
Mortality rates for the flu
at ages 75 and older
are 50 times higher
than those below age 65.
Nonetheless,
the CDC recommends
everyone over the age
of 6 months
get a routine annual flu shot
every year,
if for no other reason than
to help prevent transmission
to the more vulnerable.
The cruel irony
is that older adults,
the ones who need protection
the most,
acquire less robust protection
from flu shots
due to waning immunity with age.
Depending on the season,
vaccination typically reduces
the risk of getting the flu
by about 40 to 50 percent.
So, in healthy adults,
we can say
with moderate certainty
we can decrease the risk
of getting it
from like 2 percent each year
down to just under 1 percent.
Among older adults,
even if you get a similar
relative risk reduction,
from 6 percent
down to 2.4 percent,
since the risk is higher
and the consequences greater,
the absolute benefits
are greater too.
In the Northern Hemisphere,
the flu season can start
as early as September
and go as late as March.
The problem
with getting vaccinated
too early in the season
is that immunity might wane
before the season is over,
especially in older adults.
So, it might be good to wait
until October,
but getting it at any time
throughout the season
is preferable to not getting
vaccinated at all.
Yes, the influenza vaccine can
cause Guillain-Barré syndrome,
an autoimmune attack
on your nerves
that can leave you paralyzed
for weeks,
but so too can getting the flu.
There may be
1 to 2 additional cases
of Guillain-Barré
per million vaccinations
versus about 17 extra cases
per million contacts
with the flu virus.
So, you're much more likely
to be temporarily paralyzed
by the flu than the flu shot,
but since it takes vaccinating
about 30 older people
to prevent one case of the flu,
getting vaccinated
would still, in expectation,
raise your overall
Guillain-Barré risk.
But the reason flu shots
are recommended
is not to lower risk of some
obscure autoimmune syndrome
but to reduce the common,
and potentially devastating,
impacts of the flu
that extend well beyond
just the respiratory infection.
In the week following
a confirmed flu infection,
the risk
of having a heart attack
shoots up six-fold.
The inflammation of infection
can destabilize
atherosclerotic plaques,
constrict arteries,
and make the blood
more liable to clot.
So, might flu vaccinations
save lives
in more ways than one?
That's why indirectly
the flu may kill
up to three times more.
Those who get their flu shots
are indeed less likely to die
from cardiovascular disease
in a given year as well
as all causes put together.
In other words, those who get
regular flu shots live,
on average, longer lives.
But who disproportionally
gets flu shots?
White, married, nonsmokers
of a higher social class,
with higher education,
higher incomes,
and health insurance.
You can't tell
if it's truly cause-and-effect
until you put it to the test.
There have been four
randomized controlled trials,
flu shots versus placebo shots,
in those with
pre-existing heart disease,
and overall,
those who got the real shots
had a 56 percent lower chance
of dying
from cardiovascular disease
and a 47 percent lower chance
of dying
from all causes put together.
So, flu shots really can be
an extraordinary life-saver.
Whether the observational data
showing fewer deaths
across the board,
even among those without
pre-existing heart disease,
similarly pans out is,
as of yet, unknown,
but if you notice
for secondary prevention
the randomized
controlled trials
showed even more protection
than the observational studies
hinted at.
Given the benefits,
overcoming vaccine hesitancy
should be as simple
as correcting misinformation,
but sadly,
debunking vaccine myths
may actually backfire.
Busting the myth that
inactivated flu shots,
the type given to older adults,
can give you the flu
surprisingly makes people
even less likely to get it.
Similarly,
correcting the falsehood
that MMR vaccines
cause autism
or that pertussis vaccination
causes as many side effects
as people think
paradoxically makes people
less inclined to vaccinate.
The researchers conclude
"correcting vaccine myths
may not be an effective approach
to promoting vaccination."